<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-29T10:11:49+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A HCI professional striving to develop more fair user representation </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Hidden Costs of AI Development - What I’ve Learned Working Across Global Tech Ecosystems</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/AI-Ethics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hidden Costs of AI Development - What I’ve Learned Working Across Global Tech Ecosystems"/><published>2025-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/AI-Ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/AI-Ethics/"><![CDATA[<p>Through my work as an AI Tech Lead across startups, enterprises, and government projects spanning Pakistan, the US, Ireland, and France, I’ve witnessed firsthand how the current AI development paradigm creates unequal relationships between technology-producing and technology-consuming regions. This isn’t an abstract critique—it’s based on real observations from the ground about data flows, labor practices, and whose voices shape AI development.</p> <p>Over the past seven years, I’ve had the privilege of working on AI projects across multiple continents—from aerospace applications in Pakistan to startup ecosystems in Ireland, from enterprise solutions in the Caribbean to design innovation in France. What I’ve observed isn’t the democratizing force that AI advocates often promise, but a more complex reality where the benefits and burdens of AI development are unevenly distributed.</p> <div class="key-insight"> <strong>Key Insight:</strong> The current AI ecosystem doesn't just have bias problems—it has structural inequality problems that go far deeper than algorithmic fairness. </div> <p>This post reflects on what I’ve learned about the global AI ecosystem and raises questions we need to address as the technology becomes more pervasive.</p> <h2 id="the-data-extraction-reality">The Data Extraction Reality</h2> <p>During my time leading data science teams at various organizations, I’ve seen how data flows in the global AI economy. When we built analytics frameworks for enterprise clients, the pattern was consistent: data generated in emerging markets often gets processed and monetized by platforms headquartered elsewhere<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p> <div class="data-flow-diagram"> Lagos User Data → Silicon Valley AI Company → Licensed Back to Lagos Banks </div> <p>Take mobile financial services, an area I’ve worked on extensively. While innovations like M-Pesa originated in Kenya<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, the behavioral data generated by millions of users across Africa increasingly flows to Western AI companies building credit scoring and fraud detection systems. The insights derived from this data—understanding spending patterns, predicting financial behavior, optimizing user interfaces—become intellectual property that’s then licensed back to local financial institutions<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.</p> <p>This isn’t inherently problematic, but it raises questions about value distribution. When a startup in Silicon Valley uses transaction data from Lagos to improve their algorithm, who benefits from that improvement? Usually, it’s the shareholders of the Silicon Valley company, not the Lagos users whose behavior created the training data.</p> <d-footnote>This pattern mirrors historical resource extraction, where raw materials were shipped from colonies to metropolitan centers for processing, then sold back as finished goods.</d-footnote> <h2 id="the-invisible-workforce">The Invisible Workforce</h2> <p>Through platforms like Omdena, where I led machine learning projects for social impact, I regularly worked with data scientists and ML engineers from across the Global South. The talent and dedication were extraordinary, but the economic dynamics were troubling.</p> <p>The global AI workforce structure reveals concerning patterns about how labor and profits are distributed:</p> <div class="l-body"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/ai-workforce-flow.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <p>Many of the data annotation and model training tasks that make AI systems possible are outsourced to countries where labor costs are lower<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. I’ve seen brilliant engineers in Pakistan, India, and the Philippines working on cutting-edge AI projects for a fraction of what their counterparts in Silicon Valley earn for similar work.</p> <p>Content moderation—the essential but traumatic work of training AI systems to recognize harmful content—is disproportionately performed by workers in Kenya, the Philippines, and other countries where Western tech companies can hire talent cheaply<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>. These workers face significant psychological risks while protecting users in wealthier countries from disturbing content.</p> <h2 id="language-and-cultural-bias-in-practice">Language and Cultural Bias in Practice</h2> <p>While building LLM-based solutions like <strong>Bob-The Startup Advisor</strong> and <strong>Sandy-The Financial Advisor</strong>, I encountered the limitations of current AI models firsthand. Despite claims of multilingual capability, these systems struggle with non-English contexts in ways that go beyond simple translation.</p> <p>Large language models trained primarily on English text exhibit systematic biases when dealing with non-Western concepts<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>. When I tested financial advisory models with questions about Islamic banking principles or traditional business practices common in South Asian markets, the responses were often inadequate or culturally inappropriate.</p> <details><summary>Example: Testing Cultural Context</summary> <p>When I asked my financial advisor LLM about <em>hawala</em> (traditional Islamic money transfer), it provided generic responses about “informal banking” without understanding the cultural and religious principles that make hawala a legitimate and important financial instrument in many communities.</p> </details> <p>This isn’t just a technical limitation—it reflects whose knowledge and perspectives are valued in AI training data. The vast majority of text used to train large language models comes from English-language sources, primarily from Western contexts<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>. Local knowledge systems, indigenous practices, and non-Western ways of organizing information are systematically underrepresented.</p> <h2 id="the-innovation-periphery">The Innovation Periphery</h2> <p>One of the most frustrating aspects of the current AI ecosystem is how innovation is perceived and valued. During my MBA at Rennes School of Business, I studied how technological innovation is often framed as flowing from “centers” (Silicon Valley, Boston, London) to “peripheries” (everywhere else).</p> <p>The following chart illustrates how AI investment is concentrated in wealthy regions:</p> <div class="l-body"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/ai-investment-distribution.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <p>This framing ignores the reality I’ve witnessed: incredible innovation happening across the Global South, often out of necessity rather than venture capital abundance. The aerospace projects I worked on in Pakistan involved sophisticated optimization algorithms developed under resource constraints that would be unimaginable in Western tech companies.</p> <p>Yet these innovations rarely receive global recognition or investment. The AI research emerging from universities in Nigeria, Pakistan, Brazil, or India is often overlooked by major conferences and journals, which maintain editorial boards dominated by Western institutions<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>.</p> <h2 id="a-more-nuanced-path-forward">A More Nuanced Path Forward</h2> <p>I’m not arguing that all AI development should be localized or that global collaboration is inherently problematic. The projects I’ve worked on have benefited enormously from international collaboration and knowledge sharing.</p> <p>But we need more honest conversations about power dynamics in AI development. Some concrete steps that could help:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Equitable Partnership Models</strong>: When AI companies use data from emerging markets, they should share the value created, not just extract insights<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Diverse Training Data</strong>: Deliberate efforts to include non-Western knowledge sources in AI training data, with proper compensation and attribution to source communities<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Local AI Capacity Building</strong>: Investment in AI research institutions and startups in the Global South, not just outsourcing implementation work<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Ethical Labor Practices</strong>: Fair compensation and psychological support for workers performing essential but difficult AI training tasks<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup>.</p> </li> </ol> <p>The following chart compares current AI value distribution with a more equitable proposed model:</p> <div class="l-body"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/ai-value-distribution.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <h2 id="questions-for-the-ai-community">Questions for the AI Community</h2> <p>As someone who has worked across this ecosystem, I’m left with questions that the AI community needs to address:</p> <ul> <li>How do we ensure that AI development serves local needs rather than just global markets?</li> <li>What does equitable participation in the AI economy actually look like?</li> <li>How can we preserve cultural diversity while benefiting from AI’s connective potential?</li> <li>Who should have control over AI systems that affect millions of people?</li> </ul> <p>These aren’t abstract philosophical questions—they’re practical challenges that will determine whether AI becomes a force for reducing or increasing global inequality.</p> <p>The technology itself is remarkable. I’ve seen AI systems optimize supply chains, predict equipment failures, and automate routine tasks in ways that genuinely improve people’s lives. But technology alone doesn’t determine outcomes—the economic and social structures around it do.</p> <p>As AI practitioners, we have a responsibility to think critically about these structures and work toward more equitable alternatives. The future of AI isn’t predetermined, but it won’t democratize itself.</p> <div class="author-bio"> <strong>About the Author:</strong> Danial Amin is an AI Tech Lead currently working on generative AI solutions for design optimization at Samsung Design Innovation Center in France. He has led AI projects across multiple continents and holds advanced degrees in both technical and business domains. You can connect with him on <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/danial-amin">LinkedIn</a> or view his technical work on <a href="https://github.com/danial-amin">GitHub</a>. </div> <hr/> <p><em>What do you think? Have you experienced similar patterns in your work with AI systems? Share your thoughts in the comments below.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>Zuboff, S. (2019). <em>The Age of Surveillance Capitalism: The Fight for a Human Future at the New Frontier of Power</em>. PublicAffairs. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>Hughes, N., &amp; Lonie, S. (2007). M-PESA: mobile money for the “unbanked” turning cellphones into 24-hour tellers in Kenya. <em>Innovations</em>, 2(1-2), 63-81. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>Aitken, R. (2017). ‘All data is credit data’: Constituting the unbanked. <em>Competition &amp; Change</em>, 21(4), 274-300. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>Gray, M. L., &amp; Suri, S. (2019). <em>Ghost Work: How to Stop Silicon Valley from Building a New Global Underclass</em>. Houghton Mifflin Harcourt. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5"> <p>Roberts, S. T. (2019). <em>Behind the Screen: Content Moderation in the Shadows of Social Media</em>. Yale University Press. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6"> <p>Bender, E. M., Gebru, T., McMillan-Major, A., &amp; Shmitchell, S. (2021). On the dangers of stochastic parrots: Can language models be too big? <em>Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency</em>, 610-623. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7"> <p>Rogers, A., Kovaleva, O., Downey, M., &amp; Rumshisky, A. (2020). What’s in your embedding? Analyzing word embedding bias in conceptual spaces. <em>Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on Gender Bias in Natural Language Processing</em>, 1-16. <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:8"> <p>Mohamed, S., Png, M. T., &amp; Isaac, W. (2020). Decolonising science–reconstructing relations. <em>eLife</em>, 9, e65546. <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:9"> <p>McDonald, S., &amp; Milne, R. (2021). Corporate power and global health governance: The example of foundation and pharmaceutical industry relations. <em>Global Social Policy</em>, 21(2), 275-297. <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:10"> <p>Blodgett, S. L., Barocas, S., Daumé III, H., &amp; Wallach, H. (2020). Language (technology) is power: A critical survey of “bias” in NLP. <em>Proceedings of the 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</em>, 5454-5476. <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:11"> <p>Adams, R. (2021). Can artificial intelligence be decolonized? <em>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</em>, 46(1-2), 176-197. <a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:12"> <p>Gillespie, T. (2018). <em>Custodians of the Internet: Platforms, Content Moderation, and the Hidden Decisions That Shape Social Media</em>. Yale University Press. <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>Danial Amin</name></author><category term="ai"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="global-south"/><category term="technology"/><category term="colonialism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Through my work as an AI Tech Lead across startups, enterprises, and government projects spanning Pakistan, the US, Ireland, and France, I've witnessed firsthand how the current AI development paradigm creates unequal relationships between technology-producing and technology-consuming regions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Generalist to Specialist - The Case for Persona-Driven AI Architecture</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/Specialist-vs-Generalist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Generalist to Specialist - The Case for Persona-Driven AI Architecture"/><published>2025-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/Specialist-vs-Generalist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/Specialist-vs-Generalist/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite advances in generative AI capabilities, enterprises continue to struggle with generic AI systems that lack specialized expertise in critical domains. Recent research indicates this is not merely an implementation challenge but a fundamental architectural limitation. The solution lies in a strategic shift: replacing monolithic generalist AI systems with purpose-built, persona-driven AI agents that can be summoned on demand for their specialized expertise.</p> <div class="key-insight"> <strong>Core Thesis:</strong> The future of enterprise AI lies not in increasingly large generalist models but in orchestrated ecosystems of specialized AI personas, each contributing unique capabilities to solve complex problems. </div> <p>This blog post outlines a research-backed framework for implementing persona-driven AI architecture and explores concrete applications across industries.</p> <h2 id="the-limitations-of-generalized-ai">The Limitations of Generalized AI</h2> <p>Current generative AI systems face inherent limitations when tasked with domain-specific challenges requiring deep expertise. As Bommasani et al. (2021) note in their landmark paper on foundation models, “The generality of foundation models creates challenges for reliability, as these models may appear competent when they are not.”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> This observation highlights a critical limitation in our current approach to AI development.</p> <div class="research-highlight"> <strong>Research Finding:</strong> A recent Gartner survey found that 45% of organizations are already using generative AI, but many report challenges with accuracy and reliability in specialized contexts[^2]. </div> <p>This underscores a fundamental challenge: generalist models struggle to maintain deep expertise across diverse domains, creating a breadth-depth tradeoff that limits their effectiveness in specialized applications.</p> <p>The following diagram illustrates the current limitations of generalized AI systems:</p> <div class="l-body"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/generalist-vs-specialist.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <h2 id="persona-as-a-framework-for-specialized-ai">Persona as a Framework for Specialized AI</h2> <p>The concept of “persona” offers a promising framework for developing specialized AI systems with distinct capabilities and areas of expertise. Rather than viewing AI as a monolithic system, a persona-driven approach creates specialized AI agents designed for specific domains and use cases.</p> <p>Research from Shen et al. (2023) demonstrates this approach in practice with their HuggingGPT system, which “collaborates with different domain-expert models to solve complex AI tasks.”<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> This multi-agent approach allows specialized components to handle specific aspects of complex tasks, similar to how different experts collaborate in human teams.</p> <p>Similarly, Dang et al. (2022) propose AgentScope, “a flexible yet sturdy framework for multi-agent LLM systems” that enables the orchestration of specialized AI models to handle complex tasks through collaboration<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. This framework provides a technical foundation for implementing persona-driven AI systems that can leverage specialized expertise without sacrificing usability.</p> <h3 id="the-persona-architecture-model">The Persona Architecture Model</h3> <div class="l-body"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/persona-architecture.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <h2 id="implementation-approaches">Implementation Approaches</h2> <p>Recent research has demonstrated multiple practical approaches to implementing specialized AI personas:</p> <h3 id="tool-based-specialization">Tool-Based Specialization</h3> <div class="implementation-box"> <strong>Approach:</strong> Foundation models adapted to master specific tools and APIs </div> <p>Lin et al. (2023) demonstrate how foundation models can be adapted to master specific tools in their ToolLLM research, enabling “large language models to master 16,000+ real-world APIs.”<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> This approach allows a foundation model to develop specialized capabilities by integrating with purpose-built tools, similar to how human experts leverage specialized instruments.</p> <h3 id="retrieval-augmented-specialization">Retrieval-Augmented Specialization</h3> <div class="implementation-box"> <strong>Approach:</strong> Dynamic access to specialized knowledge bases </div> <p>Khattab et al. (2022) propose the Demonstrate-Search-Predict framework, which combines “retrieval and language models for knowledge-intensive NLP.”<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> This approach enables AI systems to dynamically access specialized knowledge bases, allowing for deeper domain expertise without requiring all knowledge to be encoded in model parameters.</p> <h3 id="agent-based-specialization">Agent-Based Specialization</h3> <div class="implementation-box"> <strong>Approach:</strong> Targeted fine-tuning for specific domain contexts </div> <p>Zhang et al. (2023) outline an approach called AgentTuning, “enabling generalized agent abilities for LLMs,” which focuses on tuning foundation models to operate effectively as agents in specific domains<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>. This research demonstrates how foundation models can be adapted to specific contexts through targeted fine-tuning and architectural adaptations.</p> <h2 id="the-orchestration-challenge">The Orchestration Challenge</h2> <p>A critical component of persona-driven AI is the orchestration layer, which manages interactions between different specialized AI personas and routes user queries appropriately. This layer must determine which specialized persona is best suited to handle a particular query and manage transitions between personas when necessary.</p> <div class="architecture-diagram"> ┌─────────────────┐ ┌─────────────────┐ ┌─────────────────┐ │ User Query │───▶│ Orchestration │───▶│ Appropriate │ │ │ │ Layer │ │ Persona │ └─────────────────┘ └─────────────────┘ └─────────────────┘ │ ▼ ┌─────────────────┐ │ Persona Manager │ │ • Route queries │ │ • Manage state │ │ • Coordinate │ │ handoffs │ └─────────────────┘ </div> <p>Mialon et al. (2023) survey augmented language models, noting that “orchestrating different sources of augmentation is a critical component” of effective specialized AI systems<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>. Their research highlights the importance of developing robust coordination mechanisms that can effectively delegate tasks to specialized components.</p> <p>Wang et al. (2023) describe Voyager, “an open-ended embodied agent with large language models” that demonstrates how language models can dynamically plan and coordinate complex behaviors<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>. This research provides insights into how orchestration systems can effectively marshal specialized capabilities to solve complex problems.</p> <h2 id="inter-persona-communication">Inter-Persona Communication</h2> <p>Effective persona-driven AI systems require standardized protocols for communication between specialized AI agents. These protocols must enable:</p> <p><strong>Knowledge Transfer</strong>: Specialized AI personas must be able to share relevant information with one another without unnecessary duplication or loss of context.</p> <p><strong>Handoff Coordination</strong>: When a user’s needs shift from one domain to another, the system must facilitate smooth transitions between specialized AI personas.</p> <p><strong>Collaborative Problem-Solving</strong>: Complex problems often span multiple domains, requiring specialized AI personas to work together, each contributing their particular expertise.</p> <p>Yang et al. (2023) survey retrieval-augmented generation for AI-generated content, highlighting how “different generators can collaborate with different retrievers” to create more effective AI systems<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup>. This approach demonstrates how specialized components can work together through defined interfaces to achieve superior results.</p> <h2 id="ethical-considerations">Ethical Considerations</h2> <p>Persona-driven AI systems introduce specific ethical challenges that require structured approaches to ensure responsible deployment. These challenges include concerns about bias, transparency, and appropriate reliance on specialized expertise.</p> <div class="research-highlight"> <strong>Ethical Framework:</strong> Weidinger et al. (2022) examine the ethical and social risks of harm from language models, identifying key risks including "discrimination, exclusion, toxicity, information hazards, misinformation harms, malicious uses, human-computer interaction harms, environmental and socioeconomic harms."[^11] </div> <p>The development of specialized AI personas raises important questions about representation, bias, and the values embedded in these systems. As Weidinger et al. note, “different people will be affected differently” by AI systems, making it essential to consider diverse perspectives when designing specialized AI personas.</p> <details><summary>Key Ethical Considerations</summary> <p><strong>Bias Amplification</strong>: Specialized personas may amplify domain-specific biases if not carefully designed and monitored.</p> <p><strong>Transparency</strong>: Users must understand which persona is handling their request and why specific recommendations are made.</p> <p><strong>Accountability</strong>: Clear responsibility chains must exist for decisions made by specialized personas.</p> <p><strong>Fairness</strong>: Persona specialization should not create unequal access to AI capabilities across different user groups.</p> </details> <h2 id="hci-design-for-persona-driven-ai">HCI Design for Persona-Driven AI</h2> <p>Effective implementation of persona-driven AI requires specialized HCI design patterns that communicate persona capabilities, transitions, and limitations to users. Research provides insights into effective approaches.</p> <p>Amershi et al. (2019) provide guidelines for human-AI interaction, emphasizing the importance of “making clear what the system can do” and “making clear why the system did what it did.”<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup> These principles are particularly important for persona-driven AI systems, where users need to understand the capabilities and limitations of different specialized personas.</p> <h3 id="design-principles-for-persona-driven-interfaces">Design Principles for Persona-Driven Interfaces</h3> <p><strong>Persona Visibility</strong>: Users should clearly understand which specialized persona is currently active and why it was selected.</p> <p><strong>Capability Communication</strong>: Each persona should clearly communicate its areas of expertise and limitations.</p> <p><strong>Transition Management</strong>: Handoffs between personas should be smooth and transparent to users.</p> <p><strong>Trust Calibration</strong>: Users should develop appropriate trust levels for different specialized personas based on their track record and capabilities.</p> <p>Lai &amp; Tan (2019) examine human predictions with explanations, finding that explanations can significantly influence how users perceive and interact with AI systems<sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>. Their research suggests that effective explanations can help users develop appropriate trust in specialized AI personas.</p> <p>Park et al. (2018) explore multimodal explanations, demonstrating how “pointing to the evidence” can help users understand AI decisions<sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup>. This approach can be particularly valuable for specialized AI personas, helping users understand the domain-specific reasoning behind recommendations.</p> <h2 id="implementation-roadmap">Implementation Roadmap</h2> <p>For organizations seeking to implement persona-driven AI architectures, research provides guidance on effective approaches and implementation strategies:</p> <h3 id="phase-1-domain-identification-and-analysis">Phase 1: Domain Identification and Analysis</h3> <div class="l-body"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/implementation-phases.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="300px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <p><strong>Domain Identification</strong>: Identify key domains where specialized expertise would deliver significant value, focusing on areas with well-defined knowledge boundaries and clear performance metrics.</p> <p><strong>Persona Development</strong>: Develop specialized AI personas for priority domains, building on existing foundation models with domain-specific fine-tuning and augmentation.</p> <p><strong>Orchestration Layer</strong>: Implement an orchestration layer that can effectively route queries to the appropriate specialized persona and manage transitions between personas.</p> <h3 id="phase-2-user-interface-and-experience-design">Phase 2: User Interface and Experience Design</h3> <p><strong>User Interface Design</strong>: Design user interfaces that effectively communicate the capabilities and limitations of different specialized personas, helping users develop appropriate mental models.</p> <p><strong>Continuous Evaluation</strong>: Establish clear evaluation metrics that compare the performance of specialized personas against general-purpose systems, ensuring that the investment in specialization delivers measurable improvements.</p> <p>Building on the foundation models research from Bommasani et al. (2021), organizations should begin by identifying key domains where specialized expertise would deliver significant value. This process involves mapping existing business processes, identifying high-value use cases, and prioritizing domains for specialized AI development.</p> <h2 id="the-future-of-persona-driven-ai">The Future of Persona-Driven AI</h2> <p>Persona-driven AI represents a significant architectural shift from general-purpose AI systems to specialized domain experts. This approach builds on recent advances in multi-agent systems, retrieval-augmented generation, and human-computer interaction to deliver more effective AI solutions.</p> <p>As research by Shen et al. (2023) with HuggingGPT demonstrates, orchestrating specialized AI models can deliver superior results compared to monolithic approaches. Similarly, the agent-based approach outlined by Zhang et al. (2023) provides a framework for developing specialized AI capabilities that can be deployed in targeted applications.</p> <div class="key-insight"> <strong>Future Vision:</strong> The future of AI lies not in increasingly large generalist models but in orchestrated ecosystems of specialized AI personas, each contributing unique capabilities to solve complex problems. </div> <p>By embracing this approach, organizations can develop AI systems that deliver deeper domain expertise while maintaining the usability and flexibility that users expect. The persona-driven architecture represents a mature evolution of AI systems—moving beyond the “one-size-fits-all” approach to create specialized, expert-level AI assistants that can be summoned precisely when their expertise is needed.</p> <hr/> <p><em>What are your thoughts on persona-driven AI architecture? Have you experimented with specialized AI agents in your organization? Share your experiences in the comments below.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>Bommasani, R., Hudson, D. A., Adeli, E., Altman, R., Arora, S., von Arx, S., …, &amp; Liang, P. (2021). On the opportunities and risks of foundation models. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2108.07258</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.07258 <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>Shen, S., Gu, J., Chandu, K. R., Gupta, K., Nguyen, S. Q., Wang, Z., Rabinovich, M., Deng, Z., &amp; Hakkani-Tur, D. (2023). HuggingGPT: Solving AI Tasks with ChatGPT and its Friends in HuggingFace. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.17580</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17580 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>Dang, P., Hemmatian, B., Voigt, K., Kaufman, M., &amp; Singh, S. (2022). AgentScope: A Flexible yet Sturdy Framework for Multi-Agent LLM Systems. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2402.14034</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14034 <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5"> <p>Lin, B. Y., Shen, S., Nogueira, R., Gu, J., Qu, C., Yang, Z., Zhang, Z., Yang, J., Zhang, X., Chen, W., &amp; others (2023). ToolLLM: Facilitating Large Language Models to Master 16000+ Real-world APIs. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.16789</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16789 <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6"> <p>Khattab, O., Santhanam, K., Li, X. L., Hall, D., Liang, P., Potts, C., &amp; Zaharia, M. (2022). Demonstrate-Search-Predict: Composing retrieval and language models for knowledge-intensive NLP. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2212.14024</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.14024 <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7"> <p>Zhang, T., Li, X., Yang, S., Sun, X., Geng, X., Yang, J., …, &amp; Zhang, Y. (2023). AgentTuning: Enabling Generalized Agent Abilities for LLMs. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2310.12823</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.12823 <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:8"> <p>Mialon, G., Dessì, R., Lomeli, M., Nalmpantis, C., Pasunuru, R., Raileanu, R., Rozière, B., Schick, T., Dwivedi-Yu, J., Celikyilmaz, A., &amp; others (2023). Augmented language models: a survey. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2302.07842</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07842 <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:9"> <p>Wang, P., Schucher, J., Coleman, A., Phu, P., &amp; Togelius, J. (2023). Voyager: An Open-Ended Embodied Agent with Large Language Models. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.16291</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16291 <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:10"> <p>Yang, C., Qin, Y., Du, Y., Wang, L., Chen, W., Zhang, J., &amp; Ji, H. (2023). Retrieval-augmented Generation for AI-generated Content: A Survey. <em>arXiv preprint arXiv:2302.00133</em>. https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00133 <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:12"> <p>Amershi, S., Weld, D., Vorvoreanu, M., Fourney, A., Nushi, B., Collisson, P., …, &amp; Horvitz, E. (2019). Guidelines for human-AI interaction. <em>Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</em>. https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3290605.3300233 <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:13"> <p>Lai, V., &amp; Tan, C. (2019). On Human Predictions with Explanations and Predictions of Machine Learning Models: A Case Study on Deception Detection. <em>Proceedings of the Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency</em>. https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3287560.3287590 <a href="#fnref:13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:14"> <p>Park, D. H., Hendricks, L. A., Akata, Z., Rohrbach, A., Schiele, B., Darrell, T., &amp; Rohrbach, M. (2018). Multimodal explanations: Justifying decisions and pointing to the evidence. <em>Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</em>. https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content_cvpr_2018/html/Park_Multimodal_Explanations_Justifying_CVPR_2018_paper.html <a href="#fnref:14" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>Danial Amin</name></author><category term="ai"/><category term="architecture"/><category term="personas"/><category term="multi-agent"/><category term="systems"/><category term="enterprise-ai"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Despite advances in generative AI capabilities, enterprises continue to struggle with generic AI systems that lack specialized expertise in critical domains. This research-backed framework explores how purpose-built, persona-driven AI agents can replace monolithic generalist systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with plotly.js</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with plotly.js"/><published>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/plotly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://plotly.com/javascript/">plotly</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p>Also another example chart.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This is how it looks like:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="charts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included plotly.js code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with image galleries</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with image galleries"/><published>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/"><![CDATA[<p>The images in this post are all zoomable, arranged into different mini-galleries using different libraries.</p> <h2 id="lightbox2"><a href="https://lokeshdhakar.com/projects/lightbox2/">Lightbox2</a></h2> <p><a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="photoswipe"><a href="https://photoswipe.com/">PhotoSwipe</a></h2> <div class="pswp-gallery pswp-gallery--single-column" id="gallery--getting-started"> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1669" data-pswp-height="2500" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1875" data-pswp-height="2500" data-cropped="true" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://unsplash.com" data-pswp-src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1666" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <div> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1667" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> </div> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="spotlight-js"><a href="https://nextapps-de.github.io/spotlight/">Spotlight JS</a></h2> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="venobox"><a href="https://veno.es/venobox/">Venobox</a></h2> <p><a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="images"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included image galleries could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with tabs</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with tabs"/><published>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/"><![CDATA[<p>This is how a post with <a href="https://github.com/Ovski4/jekyll-tabs">tabs</a> looks like. Note that the tabs could be used for different purposes, not only for code.</p> <h2 id="first-tabs">First tabs</h2> <p>To add tabs, use the following syntax:</p> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tabs</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">tab-name-1</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

Content 1

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">tab-name-2</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

Content 2

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtabs</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>With this you can generate visualizations like:</p> <ul id="log" class="tab" data-tab="889c5032-92e0-4521-b3d0-ac7c8e05357c" data-name="log"> <li class="active" id="log-php"> <a href="#">php </a> </li> <li id="log-js"> <a href="#">js </a> </li> <li id="log-ruby"> <a href="#">ruby </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="889c5032-92e0-4521-b3d0-ac7c8e05357c" data-name="log"> <li class="active"> <div class="language-php highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">var_dump</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'hello'</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">hello</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nx">pputs</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">hello</span><span class="dl">'</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> </ul> <h2 id="another-example">Another example</h2> <ul id="data-struct" class="tab" data-tab="a8cbf095-8d47-413d-91ce-f4e127609bfd" data-name="data-struct"> <li class="active" id="data-struct-yaml"> <a href="#">yaml </a> </li> <li id="data-struct-json"> <a href="#">json </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="a8cbf095-8d47-413d-91ce-f4e127609bfd" data-name="data-struct"> <li class="active"> <div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">hello</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">whatsup"</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">hi"</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
  </span><span class="nl">"hello"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s2">"whatsup"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"hi"</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div> </li> </ul> <h2 id="tabs-for-something-else">Tabs for something else</h2> <ul id="something-else" class="tab" data-tab="ac451d5a-4d9e-40ec-a9a8-b56ac08e1a13" data-name="something-else"> <li class="active" id="something-else-text"> <a href="#">text </a> </li> <li id="something-else-quote"> <a href="#">quote </a> </li> <li id="something-else-list"> <a href="#">list </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="ac451d5a-4d9e-40ec-a9a8-b56ac08e1a13" data-name="something-else"> <li class="active"> <p>Regular text</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>A quote</p> </blockquote> </li> <li> <p>Hipster list</p> <ul> <li>brunch</li> <li>fixie</li> <li>raybans</li> <li>messenger bag</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included tabs in a post could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with typograms</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with typograms"/><published>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/typograms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://github.com/google/typograms/">typograms</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+
</code></pre> <p>Another example:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.
</code></pre> <p>For more examples, check out the <a href="https://google.github.io/typograms/#examples">typograms documentation</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included typograms code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post that can be cited</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post that can be cited"/><published>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post that can be cited. The content of the post ends here, while the citation information is automatically provided below. The only thing needed is for you to set the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">citation</code> key in the front matter to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="citation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what a post that can be cited looks like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with pseudo code</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with pseudo code"/><published>2024-04-15T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some pseudo code rendered by <a href="https://github.com/SaswatPadhi/pseudocode.js">pseudocode</a>. The example presented here is the same as the one in the <a href="https://saswat.padhi.me/pseudocode.js/">pseudocode.js</a> documentation, with only one simple but important change: everytime you would use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$</code>, you should use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code> instead. Also, note that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pseudocode</code> key in the front matter is set to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code> to enable the rendering of pseudo code. As an example, using this code:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">pseudocode
</span><span class="sb">% This quicksort algorithm is extracted from Chapter 7, Introduction to Algorithms (3rd edition)
\begin{algorithm}
\caption{Quicksort}
\begin{algorithmic}
\PROCEDURE{Quicksort}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \IF{$$p &lt; r$$}
        \STATE $$q = $$ \CALL{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, p, q - 1$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, q + 1, r$$}
    \ENDIF
\ENDPROCEDURE
\PROCEDURE{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \STATE $$x = A[r]$$
    \STATE $$i = p - 1$$
    \FOR{$$j = p$$ \TO $$r - 1$$}
        \IF{$$A[j] &lt; x$$}
            \STATE $$i = i + 1$$
            \STATE exchange
            $$A[i]$$ with $$A[j]$$
        \ENDIF
        \STATE exchange $$A[i]$$ with $$A[r]$$
    \ENDFOR
\ENDPROCEDURE
\end{algorithmic}
\end{algorithm}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-pseudocode">% This quicksort algorithm is extracted from Chapter 7, Introduction to Algorithms (3rd edition)
\begin{algorithm}
\caption{Quicksort}
\begin{algorithmic}
\PROCEDURE{Quicksort}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \IF{$$p &lt; r$$}
        \STATE $$q = $$ \CALL{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, p, q - 1$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, q + 1, r$$}
    \ENDIF
\ENDPROCEDURE
\PROCEDURE{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \STATE $$x = A[r]$$
    \STATE $$i = p - 1$$
    \FOR{$$j = p$$ \TO $$r - 1$$}
        \IF{$$A[j] &lt; x$$}
            \STATE $$i = i + 1$$
            \STATE exchange
            $$A[i]$$ with $$A[j]$$
        \ENDIF
        \STATE exchange $$A[i]$$ with $$A[r]$$
    \ENDFOR
\ENDPROCEDURE
\end{algorithmic}
\end{algorithm}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included pseudo code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with code diff</title><link href="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/code-diff/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with code diff"/><published>2024-01-27T19:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-27T19:22:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/code-diff</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danial-amin.github.io/blog/2024/code-diff/"><![CDATA[<p>You can display diff code by using the regular markdown syntax:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">diff
</span><span class="gh">diff --git a/sample.js b/sample.js
index 0000001..0ddf2ba
</span><span class="gd">--- a/sample.js
</span><span class="gi">+++ b/sample.js
</span><span class="p">@@ -1 +1 @@</span>
<span class="gd">-console.log("Hello World!")
</span><span class="gi">+console.log("Hello from Diff2Html!")</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gh">diff --git a/sample.js b/sample.js
index 0000001..0ddf2ba
</span><span class="gd">--- a/sample.js
</span><span class="gi">+++ b/sample.js
</span><span class="p">@@ -1 +1 @@</span>
<span class="gd">-console.log("Hello World!")
</span><span class="gi">+console.log("Hello from Diff2Html!")
</span></code></pre></div></div> <p>But this is difficult to read, specially if you have a large diff. You can use <a href="https://diff2html.xyz/">diff2html</a> to display a more readable version of the diff. For this, just use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">diff2html</code> instead of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">diff</code> for the code block language:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">diff2html
</span><span class="sb">diff --git a/sample.js b/sample.js
index 0000001..0ddf2ba
--- a/sample.js
+++ b/sample.js
@@ -1 +1 @@
-console.log("Hello World!")
+console.log("Hello from Diff2Html!")</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>If we use a longer example, for example <a href="https://github.com/rtfpessoa/diff2html/commit/c2c253d3e3f8b8b267f551e659f72b44ca2ac927">this commit from diff2html</a>, it will generate the following output:</p> <pre><code class="language-diff2html">From 2aaae31cc2a37bfff83430c2c914b140bee59b6a Mon Sep 17 00:00:00 2001
From: Rodrigo Fernandes &lt;rtfrodrigo@gmail.com&gt;
Date: Sun, 9 Oct 2016 16:41:54 +0100
Subject: [PATCH 1/2] Initial template override support

---
 scripts/hulk.js                    |  4 ++--
 src/diff2html.js                   |  3 +--
 src/file-list-printer.js           | 11 ++++++++---
 src/hoganjs-utils.js               | 29 +++++++++++++++++------------
 src/html-printer.js                |  6 ++++++
 src/line-by-line-printer.js        |  6 +++++-
 src/side-by-side-printer.js        |  6 +++++-
 test/file-list-printer-tests.js    |  2 +-
 test/hogan-cache-tests.js          | 18 +++++++++++++++---
 test/line-by-line-tests.js         |  3 +--
 test/side-by-side-printer-tests.js |  3 +--
 11 files changed, 62 insertions(+), 29 deletions(-)

diff --git a/scripts/hulk.js b/scripts/hulk.js
index 5a793c18..a4b1a4d5 100755
--- a/scripts/hulk.js
+++ b/scripts/hulk.js
@@ -173,11 +173,11 @@ function namespace(name) {
 // write a template foreach file that matches template extension
 templates = extractFiles(options.argv.remain)
   .map(function(file) {
-    var openedFile = fs.readFileSync(file, 'utf-8');
+    var openedFile = fs.readFileSync(file, 'utf-8').trim();
     var name;
     if (!openedFile) return;
     name = namespace(path.basename(file).replace(/\..*$/, ''));
-    openedFile = removeByteOrderMark(openedFile.trim());
+    openedFile = removeByteOrderMark(openedFile);
     openedFile = wrap(file, name, openedFile);
     if (!options.outputdir) return openedFile;
     fs.writeFileSync(path.join(options.outputdir, name + '.js')
diff --git a/src/diff2html.js b/src/diff2html.js
index 21b0119e..64e138f5 100644
--- a/src/diff2html.js
+++ b/src/diff2html.js
@@ -7,7 +7,6 @@

 (function() {
   var diffParser = require('./diff-parser.js').DiffParser;
-  var fileLister = require('./file-list-printer.js').FileListPrinter;
   var htmlPrinter = require('./html-printer.js').HtmlPrinter;

   function Diff2Html() {
@@ -43,7 +42,7 @@

     var fileList = '';
     if (configOrEmpty.showFiles === true) {
-      fileList = fileLister.generateFileList(diffJson, configOrEmpty);
+      fileList = htmlPrinter.generateFileListSummary(diffJson, configOrEmpty);
     }

     var diffOutput = '';
diff --git a/src/file-list-printer.js b/src/file-list-printer.js
index e408d9b2..1e0a2c61 100644
--- a/src/file-list-printer.js
+++ b/src/file-list-printer.js
@@ -8,11 +8,16 @@
 (function() {
   var printerUtils = require('./printer-utils.js').PrinterUtils;

-  var hoganUtils = require('./hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+  var hoganUtils;
+
   var baseTemplatesPath = 'file-summary';
   var iconsBaseTemplatesPath = 'icon';

-  function FileListPrinter() {
+  function FileListPrinter(config) {
+    this.config = config;
+
+    var HoganJsUtils = require('./hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+    hoganUtils = new HoganJsUtils(config);
   }

   FileListPrinter.prototype.generateFileList = function(diffFiles) {
@@ -38,5 +43,5 @@
     });
   };

-  module.exports.FileListPrinter = new FileListPrinter();
+  module.exports.FileListPrinter = FileListPrinter;
 })();
diff --git a/src/hoganjs-utils.js b/src/hoganjs-utils.js
index 9949e5fa..0dda08d7 100644
--- a/src/hoganjs-utils.js
+++ b/src/hoganjs-utils.js
@@ -8,18 +8,19 @@
 (function() {
   var fs = require('fs');
   var path = require('path');
-
   var hogan = require('hogan.js');

   var hoganTemplates = require('./templates/diff2html-templates.js');

-  var templatesPath = path.resolve(__dirname, 'templates');
+  var extraTemplates;

-  function HoganJsUtils() {
+  function HoganJsUtils(configuration) {
+    this.config = configuration || {};
+    extraTemplates = this.config.templates || {};
   }

-  HoganJsUtils.prototype.render = function(namespace, view, params, configuration) {
-    var template = this.template(namespace, view, configuration);
+  HoganJsUtils.prototype.render = function(namespace, view, params) {
+    var template = this.template(namespace, view);
     if (template) {
       return template.render(params);
     }
@@ -27,17 +28,16 @@
     return null;
   };

-  HoganJsUtils.prototype.template = function(namespace, view, configuration) {
-    var config = configuration || {};
+  HoganJsUtils.prototype.template = function(namespace, view) {
     var templateKey = this._templateKey(namespace, view);

-    return this._getTemplate(templateKey, config);
+    return this._getTemplate(templateKey);
   };

-  HoganJsUtils.prototype._getTemplate = function(templateKey, config) {
+  HoganJsUtils.prototype._getTemplate = function(templateKey) {
     var template;

-    if (!config.noCache) {
+    if (!this.config.noCache) {
       template = this._readFromCache(templateKey);
     }

@@ -53,6 +53,7 @@

     try {
       if (fs.readFileSync) {
+        var templatesPath = path.resolve(__dirname, 'templates');
         var templatePath = path.join(templatesPath, templateKey);
         var templateContent = fs.readFileSync(templatePath + '.mustache', 'utf8');
         template = hogan.compile(templateContent);
@@ -66,12 +67,16 @@
   };

   HoganJsUtils.prototype._readFromCache = function(templateKey) {
-    return hoganTemplates[templateKey];
+    return extraTemplates[templateKey] || hoganTemplates[templateKey];
   };

   HoganJsUtils.prototype._templateKey = function(namespace, view) {
     return namespace + '-' + view;
   };

-  module.exports.HoganJsUtils = new HoganJsUtils();
+  HoganJsUtils.prototype.compile = function(templateStr) {
+    return hogan.compile(templateStr);
+  };
+
+  module.exports.HoganJsUtils = HoganJsUtils;
 })();
diff --git a/src/html-printer.js b/src/html-printer.js
index 585d5b66..13f83047 100644
--- a/src/html-printer.js
+++ b/src/html-printer.js
@@ -8,6 +8,7 @@
 (function() {
   var LineByLinePrinter = require('./line-by-line-printer.js').LineByLinePrinter;
   var SideBySidePrinter = require('./side-by-side-printer.js').SideBySidePrinter;
+  var FileListPrinter = require('./file-list-printer.js').FileListPrinter;

   function HtmlPrinter() {
   }
@@ -22,5 +23,10 @@
     return sideBySidePrinter.generateSideBySideJsonHtml(diffFiles);
   };

+  HtmlPrinter.prototype.generateFileListSummary = function(diffJson, config) {
+    var fileListPrinter = new FileListPrinter(config);
+    return fileListPrinter.generateFileList(diffJson);
+  };
+
   module.exports.HtmlPrinter = new HtmlPrinter();
 })();
diff --git a/src/line-by-line-printer.js b/src/line-by-line-printer.js
index b07eb53c..d230bedd 100644
--- a/src/line-by-line-printer.js
+++ b/src/line-by-line-printer.js
@@ -11,7 +11,8 @@
   var utils = require('./utils.js').Utils;
   var Rematch = require('./rematch.js').Rematch;

-  var hoganUtils = require('./hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+  var hoganUtils;
+
   var genericTemplatesPath = 'generic';
   var baseTemplatesPath = 'line-by-line';
   var iconsBaseTemplatesPath = 'icon';
@@ -19,6 +20,9 @@

   function LineByLinePrinter(config) {
     this.config = config;
+
+    var HoganJsUtils = require('./hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+    hoganUtils = new HoganJsUtils(config);
   }

   LineByLinePrinter.prototype.makeFileDiffHtml = function(file, diffs) {
diff --git a/src/side-by-side-printer.js b/src/side-by-side-printer.js
index bbf1dc8d..5e3033b3 100644
--- a/src/side-by-side-printer.js
+++ b/src/side-by-side-printer.js
@@ -11,7 +11,8 @@
   var utils = require('./utils.js').Utils;
   var Rematch = require('./rematch.js').Rematch;

-  var hoganUtils = require('./hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+  var hoganUtils;
+
   var genericTemplatesPath = 'generic';
   var baseTemplatesPath = 'side-by-side';
   var iconsBaseTemplatesPath = 'icon';
@@ -26,6 +27,9 @@

   function SideBySidePrinter(config) {
     this.config = config;
+
+    var HoganJsUtils = require('./hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+    hoganUtils = new HoganJsUtils(config);
   }

   SideBySidePrinter.prototype.makeDiffHtml = function(file, diffs) {
diff --git a/test/file-list-printer-tests.js b/test/file-list-printer-tests.js
index a502a46f..60ea3208 100644
--- a/test/file-list-printer-tests.js
+++ b/test/file-list-printer-tests.js
@@ -1,6 +1,6 @@
 var assert = require('assert');

-var fileListPrinter = require('../src/file-list-printer.js').FileListPrinter;
+var fileListPrinter = new (require('../src/file-list-printer.js').FileListPrinter)();

 describe('FileListPrinter', function() {
   describe('generateFileList', function() {
diff --git a/test/hogan-cache-tests.js b/test/hogan-cache-tests.js
index 190bf6f8..3bb754ac 100644
--- a/test/hogan-cache-tests.js
+++ b/test/hogan-cache-tests.js
@@ -1,6 +1,6 @@
 var assert = require('assert');

-var HoganJsUtils = require('../src/hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils;
+var HoganJsUtils = new (require('../src/hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils)();
 var diffParser = require('../src/diff-parser.js').DiffParser;

 describe('HoganJsUtils', function() {
@@ -21,16 +21,28 @@ describe('HoganJsUtils', function() {
       });
       assert.equal(emptyDiffHtml, result);
     });
+
     it('should render view without cache', function() {
       var result = HoganJsUtils.render('generic', 'empty-diff', {
         contentClass: 'd2h-code-line',
         diffParser: diffParser
       }, {noCache: true});
-      assert.equal(emptyDiffHtml + '\n', result);
+      assert.equal(emptyDiffHtml, result);
     });
+
     it('should return null if template is missing', function() {
-      var result = HoganJsUtils.render('generic', 'missing-template', {}, {noCache: true});
+      var hoganUtils = new (require('../src/hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils)({noCache: true});
+      var result = hoganUtils.render('generic', 'missing-template', {});
       assert.equal(null, result);
     });
+
+    it('should allow templates to be overridden', function() {
+      var emptyDiffTemplate = HoganJsUtils.compile('&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;');
+
+      var config = {templates: {'generic-empty-diff': emptyDiffTemplate}};
+      var hoganUtils = new (require('../src/hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils)(config);
+      var result = hoganUtils.render('generic', 'empty-diff', {myName: 'Rodrigo Fernandes'});
+      assert.equal('&lt;p&gt;Rodrigo Fernandes&lt;/p&gt;', result);
+    });
   });
 });
diff --git a/test/line-by-line-tests.js b/test/line-by-line-tests.js
index 1cd92073..8869b3df 100644
--- a/test/line-by-line-tests.js
+++ b/test/line-by-line-tests.js
@@ -14,7 +14,7 @@ describe('LineByLinePrinter', function() {
         '            File without changes\n' +
         '        &lt;/div&gt;\n' +
         '    &lt;/td&gt;\n' +
-        '&lt;/tr&gt;\n';
+        '&lt;/tr&gt;';

       assert.equal(expected, fileHtml);
     });
@@ -422,7 +422,6 @@ describe('LineByLinePrinter', function() {
         '        &lt;/div&gt;\n' +
         '    &lt;/td&gt;\n' +
         '&lt;/tr&gt;\n' +
-        '\n' +
         '                &lt;/tbody&gt;\n' +
         '            &lt;/table&gt;\n' +
         '        &lt;/div&gt;\n' +
diff --git a/test/side-by-side-printer-tests.js b/test/side-by-side-printer-tests.js
index 76625f8e..771daaa5 100644
--- a/test/side-by-side-printer-tests.js
+++ b/test/side-by-side-printer-tests.js
@@ -14,7 +14,7 @@ describe('SideBySidePrinter', function() {
         '            File without changes\n' +
         '        &lt;/div&gt;\n' +
         '    &lt;/td&gt;\n' +
-        '&lt;/tr&gt;\n';
+        '&lt;/tr&gt;';

       assert.equal(expectedRight, fileHtml.right);
       assert.equal(expectedLeft, fileHtml.left);
@@ -324,7 +324,6 @@ describe('SideBySidePrinter', function() {
         '        &lt;/div&gt;\n' +
         '    &lt;/td&gt;\n' +
         '&lt;/tr&gt;\n' +
-        '\n' +
         '                    &lt;/tbody&gt;\n' +
         '                &lt;/table&gt;\n' +
         '            &lt;/div&gt;\n' +

From f3cadb96677d0eb82fc2752dc3ffbf35ca9b5bdb Mon Sep 17 00:00:00 2001
From: Rodrigo Fernandes &lt;rtfrodrigo@gmail.com&gt;
Date: Sat, 15 Oct 2016 13:21:22 +0100
Subject: [PATCH 2/2] Allow uncompiled templates

---
 README.md                 |  3 +++
 src/hoganjs-utils.js      |  7 +++++++
 test/hogan-cache-tests.js | 24 +++++++++++++++++++++++-
 3 files changed, 33 insertions(+), 1 deletion(-)

diff --git a/README.md b/README.md
index 132c8a28..46909f25 100644
--- a/README.md
+++ b/README.md
@@ -98,6 +98,9 @@ The HTML output accepts a Javascript object with configuration. Possible options
   - `synchronisedScroll`: scroll both panes in side-by-side mode: `true` or `false`, default is `false`
   - `matchWordsThreshold`: similarity threshold for word matching, default is 0.25
   - `matchingMaxComparisons`: perform at most this much comparisons for line matching a block of changes, default is `2500`
+  - `templates`: object with previously compiled templates to replace parts of the html
+  - `rawTemplates`: object with raw not compiled templates to replace parts of the html
+  &gt; For more information regarding the possible templates look into [src/templates](https://github.com/rtfpessoa/diff2html/tree/master/src/templates)

 ## Diff2HtmlUI Helper

diff --git a/src/hoganjs-utils.js b/src/hoganjs-utils.js
index 0dda08d7..b2e9c275 100644
--- a/src/hoganjs-utils.js
+++ b/src/hoganjs-utils.js
@@ -17,6 +17,13 @@
   function HoganJsUtils(configuration) {
     this.config = configuration || {};
     extraTemplates = this.config.templates || {};
+
+    var rawTemplates = this.config.rawTemplates || {};
+    for (var templateName in rawTemplates) {
+      if (rawTemplates.hasOwnProperty(templateName)) {
+        if (!extraTemplates[templateName]) extraTemplates[templateName] = this.compile(rawTemplates[templateName]);
+      }
+    }
   }

   HoganJsUtils.prototype.render = function(namespace, view, params) {
diff --git a/test/hogan-cache-tests.js b/test/hogan-cache-tests.js
index 3bb754ac..a34839c0 100644
--- a/test/hogan-cache-tests.js
+++ b/test/hogan-cache-tests.js
@@ -36,7 +36,7 @@ describe('HoganJsUtils', function() {
       assert.equal(null, result);
     });

-    it('should allow templates to be overridden', function() {
+    it('should allow templates to be overridden with compiled templates', function() {
       var emptyDiffTemplate = HoganJsUtils.compile('&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;');

       var config = {templates: {'generic-empty-diff': emptyDiffTemplate}};
@@ -44,5 +44,27 @@ describe('HoganJsUtils', function() {
       var result = hoganUtils.render('generic', 'empty-diff', {myName: 'Rodrigo Fernandes'});
       assert.equal('&lt;p&gt;Rodrigo Fernandes&lt;/p&gt;', result);
     });
+
+    it('should allow templates to be overridden with uncompiled templates', function() {
+      var emptyDiffTemplate = '&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;';
+
+      var config = {rawTemplates: {'generic-empty-diff': emptyDiffTemplate}};
+      var hoganUtils = new (require('../src/hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils)(config);
+      var result = hoganUtils.render('generic', 'empty-diff', {myName: 'Rodrigo Fernandes'});
+      assert.equal('&lt;p&gt;Rodrigo Fernandes&lt;/p&gt;', result);
+    });
+
+    it('should allow templates to be overridden giving priority to compiled templates', function() {
+      var emptyDiffTemplate = HoganJsUtils.compile('&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;');
+      var emptyDiffTemplateUncompiled = '&lt;p&gt;Not used!&lt;/p&gt;';
+
+      var config = {
+        templates: {'generic-empty-diff': emptyDiffTemplate},
+        rawTemplates: {'generic-empty-diff': emptyDiffTemplateUncompiled}
+      };
+      var hoganUtils = new (require('../src/hoganjs-utils.js').HoganJsUtils)(config);
+      var result = hoganUtils.render('generic', 'empty-diff', {myName: 'Rodrigo Fernandes'});
+      assert.equal('&lt;p&gt;Rodrigo Fernandes&lt;/p&gt;', result);
+    });
   });
 });
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is how you can display code diffs]]></summary></entry></feed>